All
right, בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is כ"ו, Chaf Vav,
חנוכה שמח, Hanukkah Sameach, we pick up ten dollars, ten lines from
the bottom on
כ"ג עמוד ב', Chaf Gimel amud Bet, and it is נימא כתנאי.
Nima Kitannai. Now the issue here is about, the issue here is
a debate between
the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer whether a כהן Kohen when he does the
תרומת הדשן Terumat HaDeshen and when he takes the two parts of
the תרומת הדשן, Terumat HaDeshen, there is the ritual taking of just
the handbreadth, we'll actually speak about it in a minute how much,
but a small amount of ashes from the top and putting it
by the side of the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. That's a ritual that was
done every morning. And then the תורה Torah says ופשט את בגדיו
ולבש בגדים אחרים והוציא את הדשן אל מחוץ למחנה אל מקום טהור.
Vefashat et begadav velavash begadim acherim vehotzi et hadeshen el michutz lamachaneh
el makom tahor.
He changes his clothes, he takes the ashes outside of the camp
to a holy place, but to a pure place, but not a
holy place, outside of the מקדש. Mikdash. Now according to the simple
sense of the פסוקים, Psukim, that's all one act. First you remove
the ashes from the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, then you change your clothes, and
then you basically remove them outside of the מקדש. Mikdash. But according
to חז"ל, Chazal, this is two acts. There is the ritual act
every morning of the removal of a small amount, putting it by
the side of the ramp, and then the second part, changing your
clothes and taking the stuff out, was when there was a need,
when there were too many ashes on the altar, then you would
do a removal of the ashes like a garbage removal. And that
would be
when the תורה Torah says ופשט את בגדיו, Vefashat et begadav, he
changes his clothes. Now interesting, changes his clothes into what? Into, and
here becomes an interesting debate between the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and
רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. Well not actually, hold on, let me hold
on, because the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says
that he changes his clothes into other בגדי כהונה, Bigdei Kehunah, it's
just that they're not as nice. You don't want the clothes that
you're going to be taking the ashes out with and getting them
all dirty to be the clothes that you're going to wear the
rest of the time. So
you put on your junk clothes, but they're still בגדי כהונה, Bigdei
Kehunah, they're just not nice, they're not fancy, they're designated for this
type of a purpose. That's what he says, that's what the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma says. But presumably, if you're still doing בגדי כהונה,
Bigdei Kehunah, then presumably it is still an עבודה Avodah of the
מקדש. Mikdash. Is taking out the garbage an עבודה? Avodah? That's a
very important question. I'm serious. Taking out the significance of that. All
of us married people, maybe especially the men, understand that question, right?
Is taking out the garbage part of the עבודת המקדש? Avodat HaMikdash?
So the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says, yeah, you wear your בגדי
כהונה. Bigdei Kehunah. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says, what? This was required
by the תורה. Torah. But it doesn't mean it's called an עבודה.
Avodah. Okay, so he says that actually, he doesn't address the question
of whether you wear your בגדי כהונה, Bigdei Kehunah, but he says
a בעל מום, Ba'al Mum, even a כהן Kohen with a blemish
can do it, which presumably means that he feels that it's not
an עבודה. Avodah. You don't allow a בעל מום Ba'al Mum to
do an עבודה. Avodah. So it sounds like we have this debate
between the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer whether it is
an עבודה Avodah or not. Now that's in terms of taking out
the ashes. Comes along the
גמרא, Gemara, thank you, comes along רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish and has a question about, does the same debate
apply to the ritual of just the small amount that you do
every morning? You would think not. You would think that that ritual,
everybody agrees is an עבודה. Avodah. The whole question here is the
larger, the occasional taking out of the garbage, the occasional taking out
of the ashes. But so says ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, so that's
what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says, no, they're only debating the taking
out of the ashes, they're not talking about the ritual, that everybody
agrees is an עבודה Avodah and needs בגדי כהונה Bigdei Kehunah and
needs a כהן Kohen who is unblemished. The only debate is the
taking out of the ashes. רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, excuse me, ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish says something more radical. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says
that the same way רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would allow a כהן
Kohen with a blemish to take the ashes out of the מקדש,
Mikdash, he would allow a כהן Kohen with a blemish to actually
do the ritual every single morning, which is really shocking, which really
means that he says according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, that daily
ritual of תרומת הדשן Terumat HaDeshen is not an עבודה, Avodah, although
we've been talking about how they had the whole פייס Payis and
they had the whole lottery and the whole thing. It's not an
עבודה Avodah and you allow a כהן Kohen who actually has a
blemish to go ahead and do it. So again, to repeat, we
have a debate of the חכמים Chachamim and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
whether a בעל מום Ba'al Mum can go ahead and
do the taking out of the ashes,
and that presumably is a debate of whether it's an עבודה. Avodah.
Comes along רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, excuse me, comes along ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish and says the same debate actually applies to even the
morning removing of the ashes every single day, the morning placing, the
תרומת הדשן Terumat HaDeshen every single day, even that there is a
debate of whether there's an עבודה. Avodah. And now we have another,
an interesting thing for his proof. His proof yesterday was was that
you're allowed to do it even if you're only wearing, he reads
the פסוקים, pesukim, the פסוקים pesukim where it speaks about תרומת הדשן,
Trumat HaDeshen, ולבש הכהן מדו בד ומכנסי בד ילבש על בשרו, ve-lavash
ha-kohen mido bad u-michnesei bad yilbash al b'saro, so only refers to
two parts of the בגדים, begadim, the underwear and the cloak. It
doesn't have the belt and it doesn't have the hat. So he
says ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, look, the תורה Torah doesn't require the
כהן Kohen to wear four בגדים. begadim. So you see, it can't
be a real עבודה. avodah. So I wanted to set up a
map of this, it's getting a little confusing.
There are too many different factors going on. Thank you. You're welcome.
So
we're comparing רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish in
a minute. Okay, but first let's just talk about the
הוצאת הדשן. hotza'at ha-deshen. Okay, that's taking out the garbage.
I don't mean taking out
the ashes, it's taking out the garbage. Okay,
now because that's the debate, that's the debate we have in the
ברייתא, braita, okay, which is that taking out of the ashes. So
there's two questions here. What were the בגדים begadim that they wore?
Okay, two
or four, and there's the question about whether you can do it
with a בעל מום. ba'al mum.
Okay, can you do it with a בעל מום ba'al mum and
what were the בגדים begadim they wore? So you have the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma and the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says you can't
use a בעל מום ba'al mum and you need four בגדים. begadim.
Right, okay, yeah, so that's what, so presumably he is saying that
it is a real עבודה. avodah. Okay, that's understanding הוצאת הדשן. hotza'at
ha-deshen. Comes רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and he says you can have
a בעל מום. ba'al mum. We don't exactly know what he says
about the בגדים, begadim, but presumably according to him it's not an
עבודה. avodah. Okay, yeah. That's their debate. Now comes along רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish and they're debating what would
you say not about the הוצאת הדשן hotza'at ha-deshen but the morning
תרומת הדשן. Trumat HaDeshen. Okay, so according to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
it's the, according to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, this is only the
possibility that it's not an עבודה avodah says רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
is only by the occasional taking out of the garbage. The morning
תרומת הדשן Trumat HaDeshen everybody says is an עבודה. avodah. Nobody would
say you could use a בעל מום. ba'al mum. That makes sense.
According to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish has a
radical idea. He thinks that they're even debating the morning תרומת הדשן
Trumat HaDeshen and according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer even the morning
תרומת הדשן Trumat HaDeshen isn't an עבודה, avodah, even could be done
with a בעל מום. ba'al mum. Okay, so that's one debate. Is
this debate whether it's an עבודה avodah only by the הוצאת הדשן
hotza'at ha-deshen or even by the תרומת הדשן? Trumat HaDeshen? But comes
along ריש לקיש Reish Lakish and does something even more radical. ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish says you know what my proof is? My proof
is that the תורה Torah speaks only about using two בגדים. begadim.
Okay, and that use of only using two בגדים begadim he says,
he's got this wrong, this is gonna be confusing and nobody's... he
says actually according to the תורה Torah you don't need all the
בגדים. begadim. You don't need it when you take
out the דשן, deshen, you don't need it in the morning תרומת
הדשן. Trumat HaDeshen. Okay, so this is radical. You don't need all
four בגדים. begadim. So actually according to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, this
is the way תוספות Tosafot explains it. According to ריש לקיש, Reish
Lakish, it's not just according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer it's not
an עבודה, avodah, it's not an עבודה avodah even for the תנא
קמא. Tanna Kamma. If you don't need all the בגדי כהונה, bigdei
kehunah, it's not an עבודה. avodah. And that the whole debate is
we all agree the morning תרומת הדשן Trumat HaDeshen and the taking
out afterward, but certainly the morning תרומת הדשן Trumat HaDeshen is not
an עבודה. avodah. You don't need four בגדים. begadim. The only debate
is do we let a בעל מום ba'al mum do it? Because
even though it's not an עבודה, avodah, maybe it's פאסט נישט pasht
nisht to let a בעל מום ba'al mum do the act. But
technically speaking even a non-כהן Kohen could do it. It's not an
עבודה. avodah. It's shocking, right? You read the whole thing, ולבש הכהן
מדו בד, ve-lavash ha-kohen mido bad, הוצאת הדשן, hotza'at ha-deshen, the whole
thing sounds like this amazing עבודה. avodah. We go from saying that
not only according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is the taking out,
the occasional taking out of the garbage not an עבודה, avodah, but
according to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish everybody says nothing is an עבודה.
avodah. The whole daily morning sort of, you know, lottery that they
did, all of that wasn't an עבודה. avodah. It does not need
four בגדים. begadim. The only question is do we allow a non-כהן
Kohen to do it or בעל מום, ba'al mum, is that appropriate
or not? But technically speaking it's not an עבודה. avodah.
Even if it were an עבודה, avodah, yeah, it's possible to say
that the reason why you don't let a בעל מום ba'al mum
do it is because פאסט נישט? pasht nisht?
No, if it's an עבודה avodah a בעל מום ba'al mum can't
do an עבודה. avodah. No, no. Because what I'm not talking about
דוכנין duchaning בזמן הזה bizman hazeh which is not whatever. בעל מום
ba'al mum can't do the עבודה. avodah. So if it's, if a
בעל מום ba'al mum can do it that proves it's not an
עבודה. avodah. But according to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says that we don't know, that it is an עבודה avodah
according to the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. It's only not an עבודה
avodah according to
רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. And even this is only by the taking
out of the ashes, not by the תרומת הדשן. Trumat HaDeshen. So
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan has it, a very narrowly defined issue. The
morning תרומת הדשן Trumat HaDeshen is an עבודה, avodah, needs an unblemished
כהן, Kohen, needs all four בגדים. begadim. The taking out occasionally of
the ashes מחוץ למחנה, michutz lamachaneh, there תנא קמא Tanna Kamma would
still... Say it's an עבודה avoda. *Avodah*, only there רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer *Rebbe Eliezer* says it's not. That's the way תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*
explains it, a very narrow debate that one position רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer, *Rebbe Eliezer* only by the taking out of the ashes. But
when ריש לקיש Resh Lakish *Reish Lakish* comes along and says they
argue even by the תרומת הדשן terumat hadeshen. *Trumat HaDeshen*, and even
there they both say two בגדים begadim *Begadim*, according to him no
part of the ashes is an עבודה avoda. *Avodah*, and the only
issue is do we are we going to allow a בעל מום
ba'al mum *Baal Mum* to do it? But technically even a non-כהן
Kohen, *Kohen* could do it. Very radical position according to ריש לקיש
Resh Lakish *Reish Lakish*. Does he even mean a non-כהן Kohen *Kohen*
could do it? Well, that's an interesting question, maybe. I bet he
also... okay, so yes.
So a non-כהן Kohen *Kohen* is allowed in this area and then
disallowed on top of...
right, so that's the phrase that תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* uses is וכי
זר zar קרב אצל המזבח *vechi zar kareiv eitzel ha-mizbei’ach*. Like could
we allow a non-כהן Kohen *Kohen* to get onto the altar? Right?
So that's maybe the debate, like is he allowed in that space
or whatever, but in terms of the people that are allowed to
do the act, you know? And that so according to תוספות Tosafot
*Tosafot* it's a very according to ריש לקיש Resh Lakish *Reish Lakish*
it's a very radical idea. So clearly the emphasis is רבי יוחנן
Rebbi Yochanan *Rebbe Yochanan*, but I just wanted to make
you appreciate what is being said by saying that you only need
two בגדים bgadim, *Begadim* according to ריש לקיש Resh Lakish *Reish Lakish*'s
read. Okay, so let's keep on going. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*
says like this: לימא כתנאי *leima ketana'ei*, let's say this is connected
to a debate of תנאים *Tanna'im*. Now I lost my place. I
didn't even start. Okay, כתנאי *ketana'ei*. It is like a debate of
תנאים *Tanna'im*. על בשרו מה תלמוד לומר *Al besaro mah talmud lomar*?
It says ולבש הכהן מדו בד ומכנסי בד ילבש על בשרו *ve-lavash
ha-kohein maddo bad u-michnesei bad yillbash al besaro*. So he has the
underwear on his flesh. This is by the the תרומת הדשן terumat
hadeshen *Trumat HaDeshen*. So מה תלמוד לומר ילבש *mah talmud lomar yilbash*?
So why does it say ילבש *yilbash* על בשרו *al besaro*? Could've
just said על בשרו *al besaro*. להביא מצנפת ואבנט להרמה דברי רבי
יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Le-havi mitznefet ve-avneit le-harama, divrei Rabbi Yehuda*. So רבי
יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* says to tell you cause we're only
mentioning two of the בגדים bgadim, *Begadim*, we're only mentioning the underwear
and the cloak. So the extra word ילבש *yilbash* tells you that
the other two בגדים *Begadim*, the hat and the
belt, that's what you learn. So that clearly says you need all
four בגדים *Begadim*. רבי דוסא Rebbi Dosa, אומר *Rabbi Dosa omer* no,
לרבות בגדי כהן גדול Kohen Gadol. ביום הכיפורים *lerabbot bigdei Kohein Gadol
be-Yom Kippurim*. ילבש *Yilbash* means he can wear something that somebody else
wore. Who else wore this? The כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohein Gadol*
on יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*, cause the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol *Kohein Gadol* on יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur* wears the
same four בגדים *Begadim* as a כהן Kohen. הדיוט *Kohein Hedyot*. What
we call the white clothes of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohein
Gadol* on יום כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur* is the underwear, the
cloak, the
belt, and the
hat. So the ילבש *yilbash* means we're going to see in a
minute that according to some, what a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohein
Gadol* wears on יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur* has to be
buried and can't be used again by anybody for any other purpose.
It's a one-time use בגד *beged*. So he says no, the extra
ילבש *yilbash* that it says by the תרומת הדשן Trumas Hadeshen. *Trumat
HaDeshen* is alluding to because it says ילבש *yilbash* by the כהן
Kohen *Kohen* on יום כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur*, alluding to the
כהן Kohen. *Kohen* on יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur* to tell
us that those garments can be reused. And one thing they can
be reused for... they can be reused for any כהן Kohen *Kohen*,
but one thing would be for the תרומת הדשן Trumas Hadeshen *Trumat
HaDeshen*. That's what the extra ילבש *yilbash* is telling you, to suit
a כהן Kohen. הדיוט *Kohein Hedyot*. רבי Rebbi *Rebbe* says, says רבי
Rebbi's *Rebbe*, שתי תשובות בדבר *shtei teshuvot baddavar*, I have two responses,
two reasons to reject that idea that a normal כהן Kohen *Kohen*
can use the garments of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol. *Kohein Gadol*
from יום כיפור Yom Kippur. *Yom Kippur*. חדא *Chada*, number one, דאבנטו
של כהן גדול Kohen Gadol לא lo, זה אבנטו של כהן Cohen
הדיוט *de-avneito shel Kohein Gadol lo zeh avneito shel Kohein Hedyot*. That
you remember there's a debate what was the belt that the normal
כהן Cohen *Kohen* would wear during any day of the year. Some
said it would be like the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol. *Kohein Gadol*'s
normal belt, which would be כלאיים *kilayim*, שעטנז *shaatnez*, wool and linen.
And some said it would be just linen. Okay, the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol *Kohein Gadol* on יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur* would
be just linen. So what רבי Rebbi's *Rebbe* is saying is is
that first of all, חדא דאבנטו של כהן Cohen גדול לא lo?
זה אבנטו של כהן Cohen הדיוט *chada de-avneito shel Kohein Gadol lo
zeh avneito shel Kohein Hedyot*. The אבנט *avneit*
of the כהן Cohen גדול *Kohein Gadol* on יום כיפור Yom Kippur.
*Yom Kippur*, meaning the linen one, is not the same one that
the normal כהן Cohen *Kohen* wears. The normal כהן kohein *Kohen* wears
a שעטנז *shaatnez* one, that's debated, but רבי Rebbi *Rebbe* is saying
the normal כהן kohein *Kohen* wears a שעטנז *shaatnez* one, and therefore
he says, and the כהן kohein, גדול *Kohein Gadol*'s one on יום
כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*, linen, can't be worn by the normal
כהן kohein? *Kohen*. So number one, just technically you can't reuse it
cause it's the wrong type of a garment. The כהן kohein גדול
*Kohein Gadol*'s on יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur* is linen and
the normal כהן kohein הדיוט *Kohein Hedyot*'s is שעטנז *shaatnez*. ועוד *Ve-od*,
here's another reason you can't use it. בגדים שנשתמש בהן קדושה kedushah
חמורה תשמש בהן קדושה קלה *Bigadim shenishtamesh bahen kedusha chamura teshamesh bahen
kedusha kala*? How could you say that the garments worn by the
כהן kohein גדול *Kohein Gadol* on יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*
can be worn by a normal כהן kohein *Kohen* the rest of
the year? It was used for such a weighty קדושה *kedusha*, you're
going to use it for a light one? אלא מה תלמוד לומר
ילבש *Ella mah talmud lomar yilbash*? So what does the extra word
ילבש *yilbash* come to teach me if not to tell me that
you can reuse the garments of a כהן kohein הדיוט *Kohein Hedyot*
of a כהן kohein גדול *Kohein Gadol*? לרבות השחקים *Lerabbot hashachakim*, to
include even garments that are worn and they're not fresh and brand
new, even when they're starting to get worn, you can still wear
them. You don't need to always use although ideally you should be
using very nice garments, but you can use for the garments of
a כהן kohein *Kohen* even garments you can keep on wearing them
even after they've been worn for a good period of time. Okay,
now that we're discussing those פסוקים psukim *pesukim*, okay, it's we go
on and it says והניחם שם vehinicham sham, *ve-hinnicham sham*. So this
is now talking about what do you call it not about the
תרומת הדשן Trumas Hadeshen *Trumat HaDeshen* but this is talking about the
כהן kohein גדול *Kohein Gadol*. It says after the כהן kohein גדול
*Kohein Gadol* finishes his service on יום כיפור Yom Kippur. *Yom Kippur*
he takes off... garments and leaves them there. So what we just
implicitly had a debate about before is, can you reuse the garments
of the כהן kohein. גדול from יום כיפור Yom Kippur for the
rest of the year? So now we're going to look at that
based on this פסוק pasuk that says after he takes off his
garments on יום כיפור Yom Kippur at the end of יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur, he leaves them there. והניחם שם, what does that mean?
מלמד שטעונים גניזה. melamed sheteunim geniza. So רבי Rebbi says that means
that they have to be buried, that they can't be used by
anybody else, not by another יום כיפור Yom Kippur. כהן, kohein not
by another כהן kohein on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur and not by
a normal כהן during the rest of the year. That's רבי's Rebbi
position. You can't reuse the garments of a כהן גדול. רבי דוסא,
Rebbi Dosa who if you remember a minute ago רבי דוסא Rebbi
Dosa. said that they can be used by another כהן during the
rest of the year, so what does he say it means when
it says you leave them
there? אומר ראויים הם לכהן הדיוט. omer reuyim hen leKohen Hedyot. They
can as I just got through saying, says רבי דוסא. Rebbi Dosa:
I say the garments of a כהן גדול can be used by
another כהן. ומה תלמוד לומר והניחם שם, uma talmud lomar vehinicham sham,
so why does it say after יום כיפור Yom Kippur, he leaves
them there? שלא ישתמש בהם ליום כיפורים אחר, shelo yishtamesh bahem leyom
kippurim acher, not use it for another יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. This
is quite a fascinating idea, I'm trying to get my head around
the logic behind it. He says these garments that were used by
the כהן גדול on יום כיפור Yom Kippur, cannot be used again
on another יום כיפור. But they can be used by a normal
כהן during the rest of the
year, right? Obviously the statement is more being made about יום כיפור
than about the garments, right? Each יום כיפור is special and each
יום כיפור needs to
start afresh, needs its own special garments made for just this יום
כיפור. Whereas the garments themselves, yeah why not reuse the garments? There's
no weight attached to the garments and what they were used for,
the significance is that יום כיפור demands new garments, not that the
garments can't be reused. So that's his position. So there's an interesting
debate here. Can you use the garments of the כהן גדול after
יום כיפור or the garments themselves once used have to be buried?
That's רבי's position. Or רבי דוסא: Rebbi Dosa No, they can be
reused during the rest of the year, just not on יום כיפור,
but they can be used during the rest of the year. That's
one debate, and they debated around the word of what does it
mean to leave it there after the כהן גדול takes them off?
What does it mean when it says by the taking of the
דשן, deshen, יולבש? yulbash? Is that to tell you you can reuse
it or is that not to tell you you can reuse from
another time? But what the גמרא, Gemara purpose of the גמרא Gemara
bringing it here, is the first opinion says יולבש yulbash means to
tell you not just two garments but all four garments. So why
did the other two opinions that didn't use that word יולבש yulbash
to teach you all four garments, why didn't they use it to
teach you all four garments? Maybe they say two garments is enough,
maybe that's like ריש לקיש'ס Reish Lakish's position. Is that clear? Meaning
you had a debate here around the word יולבש yulbash by the
תרומת הדשן. Trumas Hadeshen, The first opinion רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda said
to teach you all four garments are needed although the תורה Torah
only mentions two, you need all four. רבי and רבי דוסא Rebbi
Dosa talk about using the garments of a כהן גדול. They are
not talking about four garments. So maybe that says they don't need
four garments. Let's just see the גמרא'ס Gemara's answer. The גמרא Gemara
says מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי, mai lav be'ha kamiflegi, isn't this the
debate? מר סבר עבודה היא, Mar savar avoda hi, and here the
גמרא Gemara spells it out very clearly, רבי יהודה says you need
four garments, says it's an עבודה. avoda, ומר סבר לאו עבודה היא,
u'Mar savar lav avoda hi, and רבי and רבי דוסא Rebbi Dosa
that use יולבש yulbash to teach you something else presumably they don't
need four garments, so they would say it's only two garments, it's
not an עבודה. avoda. גמרא Gemara says לא, no, that's not the
debate. דכולי עלמא עבודה היא, de'kulei alma avoda hi, thank you for
restoring the world the way it should be. Everybody says it's an
עבודה, avodah, everybody says you need four garments. אלא בהא קמיפלגי, ela
be'ha kamiflegi, this is the debate. מר סבר צריכא קרא לרבויי, Mar
savar tzricha kra leribuyei, רבי יהודה says it says two, so it
only says two, you need an extra יולבש yulbash to tell you
four. ומר סבר לא צריכא קרא לרבויי, u'Mar savar lo tzricha kra
leribuyei, and רבי and רבי דוסא would say we didn't say you
needed יולבש yulbash to tell you that, not because we disagreed but
because it's so obvious. אלא מאי? ela mai? Of course, if the
תורה Torah says two garments, it's just speaking in shorthand, of course
you need all four! Why would you think you wouldn't need all
four? This is clearly an עבודה. avodah So יולבש yulbash doesn't need
to tell you four garments, that's obvious, יולבש yulbash is telling you
something else about reusing the garments of the כהן גדול on יום
כיפור. Everybody agrees you need all four garments for the תרומת הדשן
Trumas Hadeshen? like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, and the whole debate is
about whether you need the word יולבש yulbash to teach you that
or יולבש yulbash to teach you something else about can you reuse
the garments of the כהן גדול. Dov, you had a question?
Yeah, is it implicit in this debate also the extended idea of
תשמישי קדושה? tashmishei kedusha? In other words, your תפילין tefillin wear out,
can I use it for something else, whereas the רמב"ם Rambam says
your ציציות tzitziot wear out, you cut them off and you
throw
them out?
It's related. The בגדים of the כהן גדול are more קדוש kadosh
themselves that they've been sanctified rather than just תשמישי קדושה. tashmishei kedusha.
There's also a difference between
תשמישי מצוה tashmishei mitzvah and תשמישי קדושה. tashmishei kedusha. תשמישי מצוה tashmishei
mitzvah like a מצוה mitzvah object like ציציות tzitziot and a לולב.
lulav. תשמישי קדושה tashmishei kedusha are things related to actually like שם
השם Shem Hashem which is like תפילין tefillin because of the קלפים,
klafim, the boxes of the תפילין tefillin and so on. The mantle
of the ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. This if you were just thinking
about the fact
that But the fact is they're connected to the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash and they actually are sanctified, they are, so they're actual קדוש
kadosh themselves. But it is related and תוספות Tosafot actually has that
question that according to here, that's up rather a little lower, but
according to again, it's according to this debate, right, the interesting thing
is again, you have תנא קמא Tanna Kamma saying, here, we can
do it like this. תנא קמא Tanna Kamma would say that it
has to be a לא בעל מום lo ba'al mum and ארבעה
בגדים, arba'ah bgadim, right, and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer here says, it
can even be a בעל מום ba'al mum and we don't know
we don't know how many בגדים, right? So maybe he doesn't need
any בגדים, right? Maybe he says you can even wear בגדי חול.
bigdei chol. Okay, but according to ריש לקיש Resh Lakish. who comes
along and says so this is their debate about whether it's an
עבודה, avodah. an עבודה avodah, and he says not an עבודה. avodah,
Right, but comes along ריש לקיש Resh Lakish and besides saying that
they debate not only the taking out of the ashes but even
the תרומת הדשן. trumas hadeshen. According to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish, that
comes along that says that even according to תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
it's פשיטא pshuto and this would be not an עבודה, avodah, right,
that's what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says, which is wild, but then
he but then תוספות Tosafot has a question: how is he wearing
בגדי כהונה bigdei kehunah if it's not an עבודה, avodah. right? So
he has to have a whole discussion about can you wear בגדי
כהונה bigdei kehunah for a non-עבודה, avodah which is a discussion in
the גמרא Gemara whether בגדי כהונה ניתנו ליהנות בהם או לא ניתנו
ליהנות בהם. bigdei kehunah nitnu lehanos bahem o lo nitnu lehanos bahem.
Can they be used for other purposes or not? Okay, that's according
to ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish, Okay, but again, who restored the world
and its natural order? Anyway, as an עבודה. avodah But again, according
to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish that you can have it's not an
עבודה avoda and it's even by the תרומת הדשן trumas hadeshen and
again תוספות says that technically if everybody agrees it's not an עבודה
avoda. even the לא בעל מום lo ba'al mum is just because
of whether it's appropriate or not.
Right, so the issue of תשמישי קדושה Tashmishei Kedushah and the ענין
inyan of הנאה. hana'ah.
Yeah, I don't want to get into that anymore, but right.
But no, but by בגדי כהונה bigdei kehunah it's more about them
being קדוש, kadosh, not just תשמישי tashmishei and it's less about הנאה.
hana'ah. הנאה Hana'ah is more of מעילה me'ilah related, yes.
We've gotten a little distant from the actual text of the חומש
Chumash which specifically says this to be done, these are to be
done by a כהן. It doesn't seem to make a distinction between
the two.
Absolutely, absolutely. And we're using this as a talking way to what's
coming up on the עמוד ב. amud beis.
Wait, I was a little bit confused as if the כהן is
somehow קדוש, kadosh, like
his
body is קדוש kadosh and that's why. That is, that does come
up in other סוגיות. sugyos. I don't know how much it's implied
here, but that is definitely an idea, the קדושה of the actual
person of the כהן. Let's just move further because I'm just going
to go to...
Who supplied them?
They had special people. I don't know if they were specifically כהנים
Kohanim or not, I don't know. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
continues. בעי רבי אבין. Ba'ei Rabbi Avin. So רבי אבין Rabbi Avin
asks. תרומת הדשן trumas hadeshen בכמה? bekamah? How many? Now this is
the daily ritual. This is not the removing the ashes. When you
had to remove the ashes, you just removed as much as you
needed when you had to clean it off. But when you did
the daily ritual of the תרומת הדשן, trumas hadeshen, it was a
small amount. How much ashes did you actually remove?
מתרומת מעשר ילפינן לה? Miterumas ma'aser yalfinan lah? Do we learn from
תרומת מעשר Trumas Ma'aser where the תורה Torah says
והרימותם, veharimosem, so it has a similar לשון lashon והרים veheirim and
therefore the תרומת מעשר Trumas Ma'aser is the תרומה trumah the לויים
Levi'im take from their מעשר, ma'aser, which is a tenth, they take
a tenth of their tenth. So is it one-tenth, that you take
like ten percent of the ashes on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, is that
what you do for the תרומת הדשן? trumas hadeshen, או מתרומת מדין
ילפינן לה? O miterumas Midyan yalfinan lah? Or do we learn it
from תרומת מדין? Trumas Midyan? If you remember when they took back
the booty from מדין, Midyan, right, it says that they gave a
gift to the, you know, to the temple and there it says
that it was one from, actually there were two, one to, two
types of gifts. Well, one was one out of fifty and one
was one out of five hundred. Okay, so now תוספות says what
about the normal תרומה trumah that says, you know, that you take
from your grain on a normal basis? Or חלה challah is called
תרומה. trumah. So תוספות says well the normal תרומה trumah they didn't
want to say because there is not a specific quantity. Here there's
a specific amount, one-tenth, one-fiftieth, one-five hundredth. The normal תרומה trumah there's
not a specific amount that you're taking, and same by חלה, challah,
it's not a specific amount. But these two is a specific amount.
Maybe there is no...
Well, okay, let's see what the answer is. But here that's the
question: is it one-tenth, is it one-fiftieth, one-five hundredth? So the גמרא
Gemara, says תא שמע, ta shema, come
and hear. דתני רבי חייא, Detani Rabbi Chiya, רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya
taught in the ברייתא. Braisa. נאמר כאן והרים, Ne'emar kan veheirim, you
shall remove the ashes, ונאמר להלן והרים, vene'emar lehalan veheirim, you should
remove, and that's by the קומץ kometz of the מנחה mincha that
the כהן should lift off the hand-breath of the מנחה. mincha. מה
להלן בקומצו אף כאן בקומצו. Mah lehalan bikomtzo af kan bikomtzo. So
the answer is a hand-breath. Now as רש"י Rashi says, you estimate
because you don't actually stick your hand into the burning hot coal
to take a hand-breath. Okay, but it's a small amount. It's a
hand-breath. You estimate a hand-breath, at least רש"י Rashi says it's a
minimum hand-breath, so you estimate a little bit over.
I thought the whole time the ashes were the leftover ashes.
Yeah, they were the leftover ashes, but it's right there. Well, it
is true that you would move the ashes from the fire... fire-pile
aside, so it could be that they've cooled down, but some of
them could still be hot, you know? You don't know, it's been—the
thing is burning all night. Yeah, but it's true, they could be
cooled down. They're not necessarily from where the fire is, they've been
removed to the main center ash pile in the middle. Okay. אמר
רב, Amar Rav, now we're going to be, since we talked about
עבודה avoda and whether you need a כהן בעל מום Cohen baal
mum to do it, let me rephrase that. If a כהן בעל
מום Cohen baal mum could do the removing of the ashes or
could only use two בגדי כהונה, bigdei kehuna, that was a proof
that it wasn't an עבודה. avoda, So now that we're talking about
an עבודה avoda. and what sort of, what's required for an עבודה,
avoda, we get into this very important question about what are the
consequences or what the different categories of עבודה. avoda, Let's take a
look. אמר רב, Amar Rav, ארבע עבודות, arba avodos, there are four
עבודות, avodos, זר חייב עליהם מיתה. zar chayav aleihem misa. That if
a non-כהן did it, he'd be deserving of death, not in the
court but heavenly death. The תורה Torah says והזר הקרב יומת. vehazar
hakarev yumas. And the foreigner that draws close to do the עבודה,
avoda. right, will be put to death—will not be put to death,
will die, heavenly death. Okay, so even though a non-כהן cannot do
any of the עבודות, avodos, there's two categories of the עבודות. avodos.
The most weighty category, if a non-כהן does it, he's deserving of
death. A lesser category, he still transgresses but is not deserving of
death. So what are the four that you're deserving of death? מזריקה,
mizrika, the throwing of the blood, והקטרה, vehaktara, the burning of the,
it would either be a couple of things could get burned, limbs
of an אולה, ola, the innards of any קרבן, korban, it could
be the burning of incense, anything that is burned. בניסוך המים, benisuch
hamayim, the libation of water that was done on סוכות, Succot, וניסוך
היין venisuch hayayin and the pouring of wine that was done on,
with, you know, any קרבן korban that had with it the מנחה
mincha that accompanied a normal קרבן, korban, the pouring of wine.
Those four are the only ones deserving of death. לוי אמר אף
תרומת הדשן. Levi amar af trumas hadeshen. Even תרומת הדשן. trumas hadeshen.
So now you see why it's connected. Now by the way, that
shows how far this is going. Not only is תרומת הדשן trumas
hadeshen an עבודה, avoda. which was debated between the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma and רבי אליעזר, that was actually the הוצאת הדשן. hotza'as hadeshen.
But according to ריש לקיש, ריש לקיש claimed that תרומת הדשן trumas
hadeshen wasn't an עבודה. avoda, Here, nobody denies it's an עבודה. avoda.
Of course it's an עבודה, avoda, תרומת הדשן, trumas hadeshen again, like
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan that whole debate is maybe by the taking
out of the ashes, but the תרומת הדשן, trumas hadeshen? the daily
ritual, everybody says it's an עבודה. avoda Not only was it an
עבודה, avoda. but according to לוי, Levi, it's even an עבודה avoda,
that if a non-כהן does it, you get death. חייב מיתה. chayav
misa. That's pretty funny. According to ריש לקיש, a non-כהן technically could
do it. According to לוי, Levi, deserving of death. Okay, so לוי
אמר אף תרומת הדשן. Levi amar af trumas hadeshen. וכן תני לוי
בברייתא. vechain tani Levi be-Baraita. And this is what לוי Levi taught
in a ברייתא. Baraita. אף תרומת הדשן. af trumas hadeshen. Even the
תרומת הדשן. trumas hadeshen Okay, so just again to repeat, according to
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and רבי אליעזר there's a debate whether the
taking out of the ashes outside when you're cleaning the מזבח mizbeach
is an עבודה. avoda, ריש לקיש wants to claim even the תרומת
הדשן trumas hadeshen, is not an עבודה, avoda but we are rejecting
that. The תרומת הדשן trumas hadeshen. is an עבודה, avoda. the whole
debate was the taking out of the ashes, and according to לוי,
Levi, it's an עבודה avoda, that a non-כהן would get death for
doing—or would be deserving of death. Again, not in—by—in heaven. מאי טעמא
דרב? mai ta'ama d'Rav? Now what's this debate over whether תרומת הדשן
Terumat Hadeshen. is in that category or not? What's the reason of
רב Rav who does not include תרומת הדשן? terumat hadeshen. דכתיב, de-ksiv,
the verse says, ואתה ובניך אתך תשמרו את כהונתכם, ve-atah u-vanecha itcha
tishmoru es kehunaschem, you and your children with you will protect your
כהונה, kehuna, לכל דבר המזבח, le-chol devar ha-mizbeach, all things relating to
the altar, ומבית לפרוכת, u-mibeis la-paroches, and within the פרוכת, paroches, which
is the קודש הקדשים, Kodesh Hakodashim, right? Inside of where the פרוכת
paroches is. ועבדתם, va'avadtem, and you shall do the עבודה. avoda עבודת
מתנה אתן את כהונתכם. avodas matana etein es kehunaschem. I will give
your—a service of a—of gift is—I will give your כהונה. kehuna. והזר
הקרב יומת. ve-hazar ha-karev yumas. And the foreigner that draws close will
be put to death. So anything referred to in this פסוק pasuk
is deserving of death, okay? Because it ends by saying והזר הקרב
יומת. ve-hazar ha-karev yumas. So we have to understand what is this
פסוק pasuk including, because it seems like it's including everything, right? But
we only said four or maybe the five things. So how do
we get limits from this פסוק? pasuk? So let's take a look.
עבודת מתנה. avodas matana. So the first דרשה drasha is עבודת מתנה,
avodas matana, a עבודה, avoda a gift of service. So the play
on words is מתנה ליתן, matana litein, to place, an עבודה avoda,
that involves placing something. ולא עבודת סילוק, velo avodas siluk, and not
an עבודה avoda of removing something. So yes, the תרומת הדשן terumat
hadeshen. is an עבודה, avoda but it's an עבודה avoda, of removing,
it's not an עבודה avoda of placing. Okay? And therefore it is
not according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan in the category of והזר
הקרב יומת, ve-hazar ha-karev yumas, of deserving death. Now another דרשה drasha
is to explain why only those four, ועבדתם, va'avadtem, you shall do
the עבודה, avodah. so the דרשה drasha is עבודה תמה, avoda tama,
עבודה תמה, avoda tama, ולא עבודה שיש אחריה עבודה, velo avoda she-yeish
achareha avoda, a completing עבודה avodah Not an interim עבודה. avodah So
for example, there are obvious things that need a כהן that haven't
been mentioned here. What are obvious things that need a כהן by
a normal קרבן korban that haven't been mentioned? So Charlie will remind
us שחיטה sh'chita does not need a כהן, but what does need
a כהן? Everything that follows. קבלת הדם, kabalas hadam, הולכת הדם. holachas
hadam. Why only זריקה? zrika? So the answer is, those are interim
עבודות. avodas. Those are not the final step. Only the final step,
the עבודה תמה. avodah tama. So the final step is putting the
blood on the altar, burning the stuff on the altar, putting the
wine on the altar, putting the water on the altar, there's nothing
that comes after that. It has to be the final part. Now
removing the ashes is, nothing comes after that, that is the first
and final step, or the תרומת הדשן, trumas hadeshen but it's a
taking away, it's not a putting on. So they both agree you
need it to be תמה, tama, you need it to be a
final step. The debate is, can it also be an עבודה avodah,
that involves removing or is it only an עבודה avodah that involves
placing?
You ask for what purpose, what category would it be? What do
you mean what category?
It's just the end of a process, it's not the middle stage
of a process.
If it's not a final עבודה, avodah. then you don't get מיתה
misa for a non-כהן to do it. These are the criteria of
a type of an עבודה avodah? that a non-כהן gets מיתה. misa.
Well no, if a non-כהן does the קבלת הדם kabalas hadam let's
say, it's פסול. possul. The קרבן korban is פסול. possul. Okay, and
the non-כהן gets מלקות, malkus, it's an עבירה, aveira, the קרבן korban
is פסול, possul, the only point is that for the הלכה halacha
of it's so weighty that he gets מיתה, misa, there the answer
is no, but he invalidates the קרבן. korban. Okay, so that's the
debate. Okay so now how about
לוי? Levi? And what would לוי Levi say back? רבי יוחנן לכל
דבר המזבח, le'chol dvar hamizbeiach, it says for all matters of the
altar. So you want to read עבודת מתנה avodas matana only placing,
not removing. I read the verse that says all matters of the
altar which include
even removing. ורב, Verav, ההוא לאתויי שבע הזיות שבפנים ושבמצורע. hahu le'asuyei
sheva hazayos shebifnim veshebimtzora. That's to include things that are yes עבודה
תמה, avodah tama, yes they are placing, but they don't exactly involve
the altar. What are things that don't involve the altar? The sprinkling
you do inside the קודש הקודשים kodesh hakodashim on יום כיפור or
that you do against the פרוכת, paroches, right, outside of the קודש
הקודשים, kodesh hakodashim, but you don't do it on the altar. Or
מצורע mtzora you also have sprinkling of oil. These are things that
they are the final stage of a process, they are placing not
removing, but they're not on the altar. פרה אדומה? Parah adumah? Yeah,
but that's not עבודה. avodah, I mean that is לכל דבר המזבח.
le'chol dvar hamizbeiach. Ironically דבר המזבח dvar hamizbeiach would exclude them but
לכל דבר המזבח le'chol dvar hamizbeiach says even though they're not on
the altar they're included. That's what I say but not to include
this removing of the ashes. Okay. ולוי? Ve'Levi?
נפקא ליה מדבר וכל דבר. nafkah lei midavar vechol davar. The fact
it says לכל דבר le'chol dvar says I
include what רב Rav said even the sprinkling on the
פרוכת. paroches. But דבר המזבח dvar hamizbeiach includes the removing of the
ashes. ורב? Verav? דבר וכל דבר לא דריש. davar vechol davar lo
darish. רב Rav says מדבר וכל דבר, midavar vechol davar, could have
said דבר, davar, says כל דבר kol dvar in order to tell
you even the sprinklings that are done not on the altar. But
דבר המזבח dvar hamizbeiach tells you even the removing of the ashes.
ורב, Verav, and רב, Rav, דבר וכל דבר לא דריש, davar vechol
davar lo darish, he's not impressed by that. He doesn't say that
that teaches you two things. Okay. So what do we basically have?
I'm going to actually write out the פסוק pasuk because this will
be helpful. What's the פסוק? pasuk? It says, okay it says ואתה
ובניך אתך תשמרו את כהנתכם לכל דבר המזבח. v'ata u'vanecha it'cha tishmeru
es kehunaschem le'chol dvar hamizbeiach. Okay it
says תשמרו לכל
דבר המזבח.
tishmeru le'chol dvar
hamizbeiach. That's the פסוק. pasuk. ומבית לפרוכת ועבדתם, u'mibeis laparoches va'avadetem, עבודת
מתנה
avodat
matana
and then והזר הקרב יומת. vehazar hakoreiv yumos. Okay so these are
the things that if a non-כהן does he gets מיתה misa for.
So ועבדתם va'avadetem tells me עבודה
תמה,
avodah tama,
it has to be the ending. Not for example, not let's say
קבלה, kabala, הולכה, holacha, things that are interim. Okay,
that's ועבדתם. va'avadetem. עבודת מתנה avodat matana according to רב Rav is
not סילוק. siluk.
ועבדתם va'avadetem is a play on words, עבודה תמה,
avodah tama, not סילוק, siluk, okay, תרומת
הדשן.
trumas
hadeshen. That's what רב Rav says. Okay, so רב Rav says not
סילוק, siluk, מתנה, matana, נתינה. netina. Okay, so that's how you get
these basic two categories: an end process and not סילוק. siluk. What
does לוי Levi say? לוי Levi doesn't make this דרשה. drasha. So
לוי Levi says
לכל דבר המזבח, le'chol dvar hamizbeiach, okay לכל
דבר.
le'chol dvar.
And רב Rav says no, לכל דבר lechol dvar according to רב
Rav does not mean תרומת הדשן. trumas hadeshen. It means even things
that aren't on the altar. They're still תמה, tamah, they're an end
of a process, they're not סילוק, siluk, but they're not on the
altar. Like what? Like the שבע הזאות sheva haza'ot of יום כיפור,
which were on the פרוכת. parochet.
Okay, that's what רב Rav says. Yes, it's an end process. Yes,
it's not a removal. But it is not a "on the altar."
It's the sprinkling you do in the קודש קדשים Kodesh Kadashim or
on the פרוכת. parochet. Okay, and לוי Levi says no, I'm going
to learn from here that this includes anything relating to the altar
as long as it's עבודת תמה. avodat tamah. לוי Levi agrees to
this. They're really debating this is the criteria they're debating. So is
this end process and it relates to the altar? It doesn't have
to be putting on; it can even be taking off. Okay, so
now let's continue. It says like this. Okay. ואימא ve'eima says the
גמרא, Gemara
why don't I say לכל דבר המזבח lechol dvar hamizbeach כלל, klal,
עבודת מתנה avodat matanah פרט, prat, וכלל ופרט אין בכלל אלא מה
שבפרט. veklal uprat ein baklal ela mah shebaprat. עבודת מתנה avodat matanah
אין, in, עבודת סילוק avodat siluk לא? It says I still have
a question for you, לוי. Levi. You want to read לכל דבר
המזבח, lechol dvar hamizbeach,
anything relating to the altar, even removing the ashes. But after this
general statement, it says עבודת מתנה. avodat matanah. So that's like רב.
Rav. It makes a general statement but then it's clear. It has
to be something of placing something, not removing something. I don't see
how you get away with saying, "Oh look, I have a general
statement here." Afterwards, it's followed by a specific statement of עבודת מתנה.
avodat matanah. So אמר קרא, amar kra, so the פסוק pasuk says,
the answer would be the פסוק pasuk says, ולבית לפרוכת ועבדתם. uleveit
laparochet va'avadetem. המלבית לפרוכת hamilbeit laparochet הוא דעבודת מתנה ולא עבודת סילוק.
hu de'avodat matanah velo avodat siluk.
It's only inside the the curtain, meaning only in the קודש קדשים,
Kodesh Kadashim, we'll talk about let's say the whole היכל Heichal in
general, we'll say in a minute. That's where it has to be
an עבודת מתנה avodat matanah and not a removal of something. הא
בחוץ אפילו עבודת סילוק. ha bachutz afilu avodat siluk.
But outside, even removal. So comes לוי Levi and says, "You got
it. I have to admit that עבודת מתנה avodat matanah is telling
me this is the way the גמרא Gemara is saying it, only
the placing of something, not the removing of something. But the way
I'm going to limit the implications of that is I'm going to
connect this just to מבית לפרוכת." mibeit laparochet. Things that are done,
says לוי, Levi, in the היכל Heichal and in the קודש קדשים,
Kodesh Kadashim, those have to be placing not removing. What's the act
of removing that was done in the קודש קדשים? Kodesh Kadashim? There's
one thing that we talked about yesterday. The removing of the pan
of the קטורת ketoret on יום כיפור. Right afterwards, you would go
back and remove it. So that, when it's בית לפרוכת, beit laparochet,
that has to be an עבודת מתנה. avodat matanah. So this I'm
going to bracket, literally bracket, says לוי, Levi, and bracket it and
apply it only to
מבית לפרוכת. mibeit laparochet. Make it very
small.
Right, so that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to say.
How do you get away with the עבודה? avodah. So yes, I
do not need it to be to be a placing. That only
would be for בית לפרוכת. beit laparochet. My only real criteria is
עבודת תמה. avodat tamah. So the גמרא's Gemara, going to say, "How
can you bracket this and put this just on בית לפרוכת beit
laparochet and not bracket עבודת תמה?" avodat tamah?
So let's take a look. Right, it's still a removal, not
a placing.
Exactly. Exactly. Exactly. Says the גמרא, Gemara אי הכי ועבדתם נמי מבית
לפרוכת הוא דעבודת תמה ולא עבודה שיש אחריה עבודה. ee hachi va'avadetem
nami mibeit laparochet hu de'avodat tamah velo avodah sheyesh achareha avodah. If
that's true, when it says
ועבדתם, va'avadetem, we should also say the idea that you need an
עבודת תמה, avodat tamah, an end of the process, is only things
that are in the
קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kadashim. הא בחוץ אפילו עבודה שיש אחריה עבודה. ha
bachutz afilu avodah sheyesh achareha avodah. So outside, even if it was
an interim עבודה, avodah. it should be okay, right? If you're really
going to limit everything to מבית לפרוכת, mibeit laparochet, limit the word
ועבדתם va'avadetem as well. So the גמרא Gemara says no. ועבדתם הדור
ארביה קרא. va'avadetem hadar arbei kra. It says ועבדתם va'avadetem is reconnected
to what's above. How is it reconnected? It comes actually earlier. The
key is it has this secret ו. vav. Okay, so the ועבדתם
va'avadetem tells you it's an "and," it tells you it's connected to
the more general statement. Okay, the general so he basically says I'm
going to bracket this to מבית לפרוכת. mibeit laparochet. ועבדתם va'avadetem I'm
going to keep that criteria, the ו vav lets me keep that
as a general criteria. Okay, so do we have people a little
complicated? Are people a little confused here? All right, a little. Okay,
anyway, the basic פשט pshat of this is, we forget the פסוקים
for now, which we can. What's the basic פשט? pshat?
According to רב, Rav, you need it to be תמה tamah ולא
סילוק. velo siluk. Okay, those are his two criteria.
Two. And according to לוי... Levi... It's a path. If it is
בחוץ *bachutz* then it is going to be it only needs to
be עבודה תמה avoda tama *avodah tamah*, okay, and if it is
בפנים bifnim, מבית לפרוכת *bifnim mibeit laparochet* then he says you need
תמה ולא ve-lo? סילוק siluk, *tamah velo siluk*. Your criteria, this is
the way the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says it when it's מבית לפרוכת
*mibeit laparochet*. But outside it doesn't have to be בלא סילוק *belo
siluk* so according to him תרומת הדשן trumas hadeshen *terumat hadeshen* is
included. תרומת הדשן
*terumat hadeshen* is included, okay, because he only has the תמה *tamah*
criteria. Okay, so now let's take a look. Now לוי Levi, *Levi*
is going to be the interesting one because לוי Levi. *Levi* has
a difference בחוץ *bachutz* and בפנים *bifnim* so we're going to have
give us an opportunity to explore that. Let's take a look. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. בעי רבא *baei Rava*, רבא
*Rava* asked, עבודת סילוק avodas siluk? בהיכל מהו *avodat siluk behaichal mahu*.
So I already called it בפנים *bifnim* and בחוץ *bachutz* but technically
the פסוק *pasuk* said מבית לפרוכת *mibeit laparochet* which is only the
קודש קודשים *kodesh kodashim*. So what would be the story according to
לוי Levi, *Levi* by a removal which for him is only a
problem only like an exclusion when it's מבית לפרוכת *mibeit laparochet*. What
about a removal in the היכל Heichal, *heichal*? Where would you remove
things in the היכל Heichal, *heichal*? You would remove let's say you
cleaned the מנורה menorah. *menorah* right on a daily basis. You remove
the ashes of the מנורה menorah *menorah*. That would be a type
of a removal. Okay, you'd remove so what would be the story
there? מהו *mahu*? בפנים דאמינן ליה *bifnim daminan leih*? Do we say
it's like מבית לפרוכת *mibeit laparochet* like the קודש קודשים *kodesh kodashim*
where that's where the תורה *Torah* says that it has that it
excludes an עבודת סילוק *avodat siluk*? או לחוץ דאמינן ליה *o lachutz
daminan leih*? Or do we compare it to outside? הדר פשטה *hadar
pashata* then he
concluded. מבית ומבית *mibeit umibeit*. Since it doesn't just say מבית לפרוכת
*mibeit laparochet* but says an extra ו *vav* and ל *lamed* ולמבית
*ulemibeit* so according to him that's this this would include בפנים *bifnim*
which would be both the היכל *heichal* and the דביר *devir* and
the קודש קודשים *kodesh kodashim*. Okay, since it says ולמבית לפרוכת *ulemibeit
laparochet* the extra ולמבית *ulemibeit* comes to tell you anywhere inside. So
anyway by the way I want you to look notice the irony.
According to לוי *Levi* it's easier for a זר zar *zar* to
be חייב chayav, *chayav* outside the kodesh, בחוץ *bachutz*, right, more things
a זר zar *zar* is חייב chayav *chayav* for as long as
it's עבודה תמה avoda tama, *avodah tamah*. Inside even though you say
the fact that he's going into the היכל *heichal* into the קודש
קודשים *kodesh kodashim* that already makes it so wait, no no no,
then it has to have two criteria in order for him to
be חייב chayav, *chayav*. And the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says those two
criteria are not just in the קודש קודשים *kodesh kodashim* but even
in the היכל *heichal*. So even let's say the cleaning of the
ashes of the מנורה menorah *menorah* for him would not be חייב
*chayav* because it is an עבודת סילוק *avodat siluk*.
So those are the places that are roofed, right, that are roofed?
Yeah, yes, those are roofed.
Not the outer... exactly, not only inside the פרוכת *parochet* קודש קודשים
*kodesh kodashim* it's inside the roofed.
Exactly, exactly. Okay, so now the גמרא *Gemara* says like this. אלא
מעתה ela meata
*ela
meata* says the גמרא *Gemara* זר zar שסידר על השולחן לא חייב
*zar shesidar al hashulchan lo chayav*. So אלא מעתה *ela meata* what's
the אלא מעתה *ela meata* saying? So according to תוספות *Tosafot* it's
it's the question is like this. The גמרא *Gemara* is trying to
get a handle on this idea of end process versus middle process.
And the way תוספות *Tosafot* frames it is if you think about
it it's a חידוש *chiddush* to say the putting of the blood
is an end process because the קרבן korban *korban* is not yet
totally complete. After you throw the blood there's more to be done
with the קרבן korban *korban*. You have to burn the inners. So
if we're going to call the putting of the blood the end
process it's because there's you're done with the blood even though there's
more to be done with the קרבן korban *korban*. So the גמרא
*Gemara* is saying like this: אלא מעתה *ela meata* if that's true
that once you're done with one thing you're even though there's other
things to be done it's called the end of a process and
the זר *zar* is חייב *chayav* I have some questions for you.
Let's see what those questions are. אלא מעתה *ela meata* says the
גמרא *Gemara* that's true
where are we?
זר שסידר *zar shesidar*
I just lost the place here. זר שסידר על השולחן לא חייב
*zar shesidar al hashulchan lo chayav*. How about putting the bread on
the שולחן shulchan? *shulchan*? Yes it's true there are other things to
be done. At the end the bread will be removed and the
incense will be burned but at least what's being done now for
the bread you're done okay and the גמרא *Gemara* takes this for
you know and that wasn't on the list. You know the list
had a very it was a very tiny list. But according to
you why isn't that considered an עבודה avodah. תמה *avodah tamah*? Why
isn't that enough? איכא סידור בזיכין *ika sidur bezichin*. No because it's
not done. There's more to be done. Yes not more to be
done with the bread but more to be done in the immediate
sort of context. You have to put the little the little spoons
of incense on the table. So איכא סידור בזיכין *ika sidur bezichin*
fine let a זר *zar* be חייב *chayav* for putting on the
spoons of incense. Again that wasn't on our list. איכא סילוק והקטרה
*ika siluk vehaktarah*. No because
that you're not done with because you're going to remove those spoons
of incense and burn up the incense on the altar in a
week from now. So you're not done with the process it's an
interim. So זר שסידר את *zar shesidar et* okay fine that's accepted.
And how about saying so let a זר *zar* be חייב *chayav*
for burning the incense? So yes a זר *zar* is חייב *chayav*.
What did our list say? Remember there were four things on our
list, right? What did our list say? Our list said, right, זריקה,
הקטרה, haktarah, what else, ניסוך המים וניסוך היין.
nisuch ha-mayim ve-nisuch ha-yayin. Okay. Funny that those get separate things. Anyway,
so, and according to Levi, it's תרומת הדשן. So there's a lot
that's not on the list. So how about all the parts about
the שולחן? So all of those are interim until you get to
the burning of the incense, and the burning of the incense is
mentioned. Okay. So now we have another question. And now you get
Hanukkah times, so pay attention. So the Gemara says like this: זר
שסידר את המנורה לחייב? zar she-sidar et ha-menorah le-hayyav? How about preparing
the Menorah, cleaning it out in the morning? Okay, although you might
say that that's a סילוק, not a whatever, but maybe according to
Levi, although it is בפנים, so I don't know. Anyway, but maybe
I don't know, you clean it and then you put it back.
You put the things back in their right place. So anyway, איכא
נתינת פתילה. ika netinat petilah. Fine. You have the placing of the
wicks even after you've cleaned it. נתן פתילה לחייב? natan petilah le-hayyav?
How about the placing of the wick? Because then you're done getting
it ready? No, איכא נתינת שמן. ika netinat shemen. You have to
place the oil. נתן שמן לחייב? natan shemen le-hayyav? How about putting
the oil? Now you're done getting it ready? איכא הדלקה. ika hadlakah.
That's not the end of the process. You're at the end of
getting it ready, but you haven't lit it. ואין לך דבר שחוצהו?
ve-ein lecha davar she-hotzehu? At any point in a process, you can
divide it into half like... Okay, fine, until you get to the
end. Until you get to the end. Now we are getting to
the end. הדליק לחייב? hidlik le-hayyav? How about lighting the Menorah? That's
not mentioned on here. So, lighting the Menorah is clearly the end
of the process. Why isn't the זר חייב מיתה? hayyav mitah? So
the Gemara says: הדלקה לאו עבודה היא. hadlakah lav avodah hi. Why?
I knew you'd find that surprising, especially on Hanukkah. Lighting the Menorah
is not an עבודה. avodah. You know, so before you were saying
it says, how can you say a non-kohen or a בעל מום
can do the דשן deshen and it says, you know, והרימו ממנו
ve-herimu mimenu etc. By the הדלקה, hadlakah, right, we have a whole
parsha starts בהעלותך את הנרות be-ha'alotecha et ha-nerot אל מול פני המנורה,
el mul penei ha-menorah, but nowhere does it say only כהנים kohanim
can do it. God told to Aaron this is what you're doing,
but maybe other people can do it. Who knows? It's not an
עבודה. avodah, Crazy, right? If anything you'd think, particularly right around Hanukkah,
you know, the central significance of the lighting of the Menorah. Not
an עבודה. avodah. ולא? Is it not? דתניא, de-tanya, we taught in
a Baraita: ונתנו בני אהרן הכהן אש על המזבח וערכו עצים על
האש. ve-natnu benei Aharon ha-kohen esh al ha-mizbe'ach ve-archu etzim al ha-esh.
So there it says בני אהרן הכהנים. benei Aharon ha-kohanim. There it
needs that it has to be kohanim. And that's putting fire on
the altar. לימד על הצתת אליתא. limed al hatzatat alita. This is
about the lighting of like the twigs. שלא תהא אלא בכהן כשר.
she-lo te-he ela be-kohen kasher. It needs a kohen kasher ובכלי שרת,
u-vicheli sharet, and if you're using like shovels or whatever they have
to be כלי שרת. kelei sharet. So you see the lighting of
the twigs is an עבודה. avodah Gemara says: Yeah, הצתת אליתא עבודה
היא, הדלקה לאו עבודה היא. hatzatat alita avodah hi, hadlakah lav avodah
hi. Lighting of the twigs is an עבודה, avodah, lighting the Menorah
is not an עבודה. avodah, Now by the way, you hear a
little bit the difference, right? Because the lighting of the twigs, first
of all, it could be an עבודה avoda, for two reasons. Number
one is it's part of the burning of the things that are
going to be burnt on the fire. And the burning of things
that are going to be burnt on the fire is an עבודה,
avoda, that's הקטרה. haktarah. And this is related to the הקטרה haktarah
that's going to be done. Okay, that's number one. Okay. Number two
is also that, you know, there, this is the way the Rambam
says it. The Rambam says the burning of the twigs is like
you're being מקטיר maktir the wood. There it's about burning the wood,
whereas the lighting of the Menorah, the point is not to burn
the wicks and to burn the oil. The point is to have
light. The wicks and the oil are the necessary fuel. Now you
wouldn't start to say the same about the logs. Logs the point
is not to burn the logs, it's to create the fire. Okay.
But since there's an עבודה, avoda, וערכו עצים על האש, ve-archu etzim
al ha-esh, somehow that makes the actual burning of it. Now I
want to read you the Rambam on what he says about this
because it is, he, I mean, he takes this Gemara to its
logical conclusion. Okay. להדליק le-hadlik is about creating light, להצית le-hatzit is
about... So the Rambam says the following. He says... One second. Oops.
Hold on a minute. The Rambam says like this. So he says
the four things. He paskens the four and not תרומת הדשן. כיצד
הקטרה? והמסדר שני גזירי עצים על המערכה הרי הוא כמקטיר איברים וחייב
מיתה שהעצים קרבן הן. ketzad haktarah? ve-ha-mesader shenei gezirei etzim al ha-ma'arachah
harei hu ke-maktir evarim ve-hayyav mitah she-ha-etzim korban hen. Okay, which is
another Gemara that the wood is considered like a type of a
korban.
The Gemara even has a discussion about putting salt on the wood
the same way you
put salt on the קרבנות. korbanot. That's how he says this. And
then he says like this. Okay. He says all the interim עבודות
avodot not. הולכת איברים. holachat evarim. He says like this. He says:
וכן הפשט וניתוח והולכת עצים למזבח כשירה בזרים, ve-chen hapshet ve-nittu'ach ve-holachat
etzim la-mizbe'ach kesherah be-zarim, שנאמר באיברים והקטיר הכהן את הכל, she-ne'emar be-evarim
ve-hiktir ha-kohen et ha-kol, זו הולכת איברים לכבש. zu holachat evarim la-kevesh.
הולכת איברים היא שצריכה כהונה ולא הולכת עצים. holachat evarim hi she-tzrichah
kehunah ve-lo holachat etzim. Okay. Then he says: וכן הדלקת הנרות כשירה
בזרים. ve-chen hadlakat ha-nerot kesherah be-zarim. It is not... It's not just
the גמרא says it's פסול pasul and you're not חייב מיתה. chayav
mita. כשרה בזרים, kesheira b'zarim, a non-כהן could light the מנורה. menorah
לפיכך אם הטיב הכהן את הנרות, lefichach im heitiv hakohein et haneirot,
if the כהן cleaned the נרות, neirot, it's fine. It's just sometimes
the כהן has to do the הטבה, hatava, that is an עבודה,
avoda, but not the הדלקה. hadlaka. והוציאם לחוץ מותר לזר להדליקן, vehotziam
lachutz mutar l'zar lehadlikan, he took the מנורה menorah out because he's
not going to have a non-כהן going into the היכל, but you
could take the מנורה menorah out. Whoever thought that you could light
the מנורה not in its right place? That's how you can take
the מנורה out and light it. Right. Very bizarre. But anyway, the
רמב"ם Rambam goes from our גמרא saying it's not an עבודה, avoda.
which in our גמרא might mean you're not חייב מיתה, chayav mita,
who knows? Technically it's not an עבודה, avoda you still need a
כהן. The רמב"ם Rambam goes so far to say that a non-כהן
can do the הדלקת הנרות. hadlakat haneirot. Okay? So it's really quite
wild. Can women do it? Presumably, it doesn't say, presumably. All right,
so now we have that. Okay, so this הדלקת נרות, hadlakas neiros,
nowhere does it say בני אהרן הכהנים, bnei Aharon hakohanim, it's not
an עבודה, avoda. anybody really in theory could do it, and that's
it. As opposed to the burning of the wood. Okay, so אלא
מעתה says the גמרא, זר שסידר את המערכה לחייב. zar shesider es
hamaracha l'chayav. So now we just mentioned that putting the wood on
is an עבודה. avoda, Is it an עבודה avoda. that you're חייב
מיתה chayav mita for? Is it an עבודה avoda, תמה or not?
So איכא סידור שני גזירי עצים, ikka sider shnei gizeira eitzim, there
are two of the still the two logs that have to be
put on. סידור שני גזירים לחייב? sider shnei gizeirim l'chayev? How about
the two logs? Right, we just mentioned that that was an עבודה.
avoda No, איכא סידור איברים, ikka sider eivarim, that's yes it's an
עבודה, avoda. it's פסול pasul if a non-כהן does it, but it's
an interim עבודה. There's going to be the parts of the קרבן
korban, and the innards of the קרבן korban, that are going to
be burned on it, so you're not חייב מיתה. chayav mita. דאמר
רבי אסי, d'amar Rabbi Assi, didn't רב אסי אמר רבי יוחנן, Rav
Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan, זר שסידר שני גזירי עצים חייב, zar shesider
shnei gizeira eitzim chayav, that you are חייב מיתה chayav mita a
זר who does the log wood? בה פליגי, beha paligi, this is
the debate. מר סבר עבודה תמה היא, mar savar avoda tama hi,
one says it is an end of a process, because it's the
end of the wood, it's of the fire, right? The קרבן is
a different thing, it's the bringing of a קרבן, you know, there
are many קרבנות korbanos that are going to be brought to it,
but this is the end of the process of making the fire.
ומר סבר לאו עבודה תמה היא. umar savar lav avoda tama hi.
No, it's only considered interim because it's only being made for the
sake of burning the קרבנות. korbanot. So yes, everybody agrees it's an
עבודה, but it's a question whether it's considered an interim עבודה or
not. And if you are חייב, it would fall under הקטרה. haktara.
That would be you'd see the logs of wood like the רמב"ם
Rambam said like a type of a קרבן, like a type of
a הקטרה. haktara. תני כוותיה דרב ותני כוותיה דלוי, tani k'vasei d'Rav
v'tani k'vasei d'Levi, we'll end with this. A ברייתא Baraita supports each
one. תני כוותיה דרב, tani k'vasei d'Rav, we learn like רב Rav
that תרומת הדשן you're not חייב for. עבודות שזר חייב עליהן מיתה,
avodos shezar chayav aleihen mita, the עבודות avodos that a זר is
חייב, זריקת הדם בין לפנים בין לפנים ולפנים, zrikas hadam bein lifnim
bein lifnim v'lifnim, the throwing of the blood, whether on the inside,
in the inner-inner, wherever, I mean, you know, whether in the היכל,
in the קודש הקודשים. Kodesh Hakodashim. והימזה בחטאת העוף, v'hamaza b'chatas ha'of,
the squirting of the blood of a bird sacrifice because it's not
the same act as throwing the blood. והמימצה, v'hamimatzei, or the squeezing
of the blood, והמקטיר v'hamaktir and the burning of the bird בעולת
העוף, b'olas ha'of, because the bird that's an עולה. olah. So it
just mentions these are forms of blood, but they're done different ways.
והמנסך, v'hamenaseich, the pouring of the wine libation, שלשה לוגין מים, shlosha
login mayim, three לוג log of water which is the minimum amount,
ושלשה לוגין יין, v'shlosha login yayin, or three לוג log of wine.
So basically it's the same thing, the blood, the burning, and the
libation. תני כוותיה דלוי, tani k'vasei d'Levi, but no תרומת הדשן. We
taught like לוי, עבודות שזר חייב עליהן מיתה, avodos shezar chayav aleihen
mita, the עבודות avodos that a זר gets מיתה, mita, המרים את
הדשן, hamayrim es hadeshen, so it starts with תרומת הדשן. That's like
לוי. המרים את הדשן, hamayrim es hadeshen, ושבע הזיות שבפנים ושבמצורע, v'sheva
hazyos shebifnim v'shebimetzora, that we mentioned before, sprinkling of the blood even
if it's not on the מזבח, mizbeach, the sprinkling that you do
on the inside on יום כיפור, the sprinkling of the oil that
you do with the מצורע. metzora. So sprinkling that you do even
if they are not on the מזבח. mizbeach. והמעלה על גבי מזבח,
v'hamaleh agabei mizbeach, and burning something on the altar, that's the הקטרה,
haktara, בין דבר כשר בין דבר פסול, bein davar kasher bein davar
pasul, even if it's invalid as long as it's something that once
put on the מזבח mizbeach is allowed to remain on the מזבח.
mizbeach. Okay, and with that we end a debate between רב Rav
and לוי, do we include תרומת הדשן on this list, which is
an עבודת סילוק? Everybody agrees you need an עבודה תמה, and the
question is how do you define what is the end of a
process? And the real shocker is is that lighting the מנורה is
not an עבודה. End with that.